Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, the awesome power of antioxidants.
And we start with an investigation
into which bean, berry, and lentil
has the highest antioxidant power.
An apple a day has been
associated with as much as
a 35 percent lower risk
of premature death,
but which apple is best?
Whichever apple
you'll eat the most.
So, eat your favorite apple.
But if you don't care
which apple you eat,
or you're just curious,
which apple has the highest
antioxidant content:
Fuji, Gala, Golden Delicious,
Granny Smith, Pink Lady,
or Red Delicious?
For apples,
Granny gets the gold,
with more than
twice as many antioxidants
than Golden Delicious apples.
Interestingly, antioxidant
content roughly corresponds
with the ability
to lower cholesterol levels
within one month
for those randomized to eat
an apple a day.
Annurca apples beat
Granny Smith, but presumably,
it's because study participants
got two Annurcas a day
versus just one of the others,
because they were
about half the size.
But two apples
even when they're half the size,
have more overall surface area,
and the magic
may be in the peel.
If you randomize people to eat
apples with or without the peel,
you see a significant boost
in artery function
within an hour
of peel consumption.
So, don't peel your apples.
For other foods, the antioxidant
spread can be even greater.
Check out nuts.
Walnuts for the win!
Followed by pecans,
then pistachios,
and who would have guessed
almonds would be
way down here at the bottom?
Walnuts also have
the highest omega-3 content,
by a large margin,
beat out other nuts
in suppressing the growth
of cancer cells
in a Petri dish.
And walnuts are
the only nuts shown
to markedly improve
human artery function.
Blackberries
beat out blueberries
for antioxidant capacity.
The beans surprised me.
What do you think fits the bill
for best bean,
at least
from an antioxidant perspective?
Want to pause and take bets?
The lowest on the leaderboard:
chickpeas.
Holy hummus!
The mightiest free radical
fighter is the fava bean,
with kidneys and pintos
neck and neck for number two.
Lentils were
another big surprise.
I would have guessed
black or red lentils
to be up there with brown
or green at the bottom.
But check this out.
Green lentils have
about four times
the antioxidant power
of red ones!
Next up, how antioxidants may
lower the risk of depression.
According to the latest
from the CDC,
the rates of all of our top 10 killers
have fallen or stabilized
except for one...
suicide.
Accumulating evidence indicates
that oxidative free radicals
may play important roles
in the development
of various neuropsychiatric disorders
including major depression.
For example, in a study of
nearly 300,000 Canadians,
greater fruit and vegetable
consumption was associated
with lower odds of depression,
psychological distress,
self-reported mood and anxiety disorders
and poor perceived mental health.
They conclude that since a
healthy diet comprised of
a high intake of fruits and vegetables
is rich in anti-oxidants,
may consequently dampen
the detrimental effects
of oxidative stress
on mental health.
But that was just
based on asking
how many fruits and veggies people ate.
If you measure the levels of
carotenoid phytonutrients
in nearly 2000 people
across the country,
a higher total blood carotenoid
level was associated
with a lower likelihood of
elevated depressive symptoms,
and there appeared to be a
dose-response relationship,
meaning the higher the levels,
the better people felt.
Lycopene, the red pigment
predominantly found in tomatoes,
but also present in watermelon,
pink grapefruit, guava, papaya,
is the most powerful antioxidant
among the carotenoid family.
In a test tube it’s about
100 times more effective
at quenching these free radicals
than vitamin E, for example.
And in a study of about a
thousand older men and women,
those who ate the
most tomato products
had about half the
odds of depression.
The researchers conclude that
a tomato-rich diet
may have a beneficial effect on the
prevention of depressive symptoms.
Higher intake of fruits
and vegetables has been found
to lead to a lower risk of
developing depression.
But if it’s the antioxidants can’t we
just take an antioxidant pill?
No, only food sources
of antioxidants
were protectively associated
with depression.
Not antioxidants from
dietary supplements.
Although plant foods and
food-derived phytochemicals
have been associated
with health benefits,
antioxidants from dietary
supplements appear to be
less beneficial and may, in fact,
be detrimental to health.
This may indicate that
the form and delivery
of the antioxidants
are important.
Alternately, the observed
association may be due
not to antioxidants at all, but
rather to other dietary factors
such as folate that also occur in fruits,
vegetables, and plant-rich diets.
In a study of thousands of
middle-aged office workers,
eating lots of processed food
was found to be a risk factor
for at least mild to moderate
depression five years later,
whereas a whole food pattern
was found to be protective.
Yes, it could be because of the high content
of antioxidants in fruits and vegetables
but could also be the folate
in greens and beans,
as some studies have suggested
an increased risk of depression
in folks who may not have
been getting enough.
Low folate levels in the blood
are associated with depression,
but since most of the early
studies were cross-sectional,
meaning a snapshot
in time,
we didn’t know if the low
folate led to depression
or the depression
led to low folate.
Maybe when you have the blues you
don’t want to eat the greens.
But since then a number of
cohort studies were published,
following people over time,
and a low dietary intake of folate
may indeed be a risk factor
for severe depression, as much
as a threefold higher risk.
Note this is dietary folate intake,
not folic acid supplements,
so they were actually
eating healthy foods.
If you give people folic acid pills
they don’t seem to work.
This may be because folate is found in
dark green leafy vegetables like spinach,
whereas folic acid is the
oxidized synthetic compound
used in food fortification
and dietary supplements
because it’s
more shelf-stable,
but may have different effects on
the body as I explored previously.
These kinds of findings
point to the importance
of antioxidant food sources RATHER
than dietary supplements.
But there was an interesting study
giving people high dose vitamin C,
also known as
ascorbic acid.
The vitamin C, but not placebo group,
experienced a decrease
in depression scores,
and also greater FSI.
What is FSI?
FSI evidently stands for
penile-vaginal intercourse,
an acronym that makes
no sense to me.
But evidently high dose
vitamin C
improves mood and
intercourse frequency,
but only in sexual partners that
don’t live with one another.
In the placebo group,
those not living together
had sex about
once a week,
and those living together a little higher,
once every five days,
but no big change
on vitamin C.
But those not living
together on vitamin C,
every other day!
The differential effect on
non-cohabitants suggests
that the mechanism is
not a peripheral one,
meaning outside of the brain,
but a central one—
some psychological change
which motivates the person
to venture forth to
have intercourse.
The mild antidepressant
effect they found
was unrelated to cohabitation
or frequency,
so it does not appear that the
depression scores improved
just because of
the improved FSI.
Finally today,
to stay out of oxidative debt,
we need to take in more
antioxidants than we use up.
The postprandial state is
a pro-oxidant state,
meaning that after each meal
free radicals are produced
as our body assimilates the food,
and so you can't just
have a bowl of berries
in the morning to
meet our minimum
daily antioxidant needs
and call it a day.
Each and every meal
should contain
high antioxidant foods, which,
if you remember, means plants.
Antioxidant rich foods originate
from the plant kingdom.
This is due to the
thousands of natural
antioxidant compounds found
naturally in plant foods.
So, for example,
consuming fruits,
which are high in
phenolic phytonutrients,
increases the antioxidant
capacity of the blood,
and when they are
consumed with
the standard American
diet high fat
and refined carbohydrate, pro-oxidant,
and pro-inflammatory’ meals,
they may help counterbalance
some of the negative effects.
Given the content
and availability
of fat and sugars in
the Western diet,
regular consumption of
phenolic-rich foods,
particularly in
conjunction with meals,
appears to be a
prudent strategy
to maintain oxidative
balance and health.
And of all fruits,
berries may be the best.
Add a glass of red wine,
which contains berry
phytonutrients from grapes,
and we can bring down
the level of oxidation,
but not blunt it completely.
So the meal needs
even more plants.
In this study, they gave people
standard breakfast items,
resulting in lots of oxidized
cholesterol in their blood stream
1,2,3,4,5,6 hours after the meal.
But all it took was
a cup of strawberries
with that same breakfast to
at least keep the meal
from contributing to
further oxidation.
Note though, without
the strawberries,
look where we'd
be at lunchtime.
Let's say we ate a standard
American diet at 6 am.
If we didn’t eat that cup of
strawberries with breakfast,
by the time lunch rolls
around we'd already be
starting out in a
hyper-oxidized state
and could just
make things worse.
Since western eating
patterns include
eating multiple meals a day,
including snacks,
one can only speculate on the
level of biological unrest.
But, at least if we had
some berries for breakfast
we'd be starting out
at baseline for lunch.
This acute protection
is likely due
to the antioxidant effects of
the strawberry phytonutrients.
Even better than baseline,
how about our meal
actually improving our
antioxidant status?
Here's measuring the
antioxidant level
of one's bloodstream
after a crappy meal.
It drops, using up our
antioxidant stores,
but eat a big bunch of
red grapes with the meal
and the antioxidant level of
our bloodstream goes up,
such that our body
is in a positive
antioxidant balance
for a few hours.
Same thing after
enough blueberries.
And imagine if in these ensuing
hours between our next meal
we were sipping green
tea or hibiscus?
We'd have this nice antioxidant
surplus all day long.
What, according to the researchers,
are the practical implications?
These data provide an
interesting perspective
for advising individuals
on food choices
when consuming a moderate to
high fat meal is unavoidable.
00:03:41,3 --> 00:03:43,04
Unavoidable?!
So, if we're like locked in a
fast food joint or something?
Well, then they suggest
chasing whatever
you’re forced to eat
with some berries.
Reminds me of those
studies on smokers
00:03:54,4 --> 00:03:58,11
I talked about, suggesting
those who smoke
should eat lots of
kale and broccoli
to reduce the oxidative
damage to their DNA.
Or...they could
just not smoke.
In a single day,
the systemic stress
of all the fat in your
blood and redox imbalance
(being in a mild pro-oxidant
state after meals)
may seem trivial.
Over time, however,
these daily insults
can lead to complicated
atherosclerosis,
contributing to hundreds of
thousands of deaths a year.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.